Guide to the Papers of Jefferson Davis documents and reference collection, 1815-2015 MS 638
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Papers of Jefferson Davis documents and reference collection
1815-2015, bulk 1850-1880
1850-1880
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University. Jefferson Davis Association
MS 638
270 Linear Feet 80 file drawers, 40 boxes, 1 card catalog
This collection includes the wealth of documentation identified from across the United States and beyond and assembled for the purpose of the publication of the Papers of Jefferson Davis, a 14-volume set, funded by the NHPRC, and other activities and persons, beginning in the 1960s and running through 2015. Many of the speeches and letters published in the edition, either in full or summarized, are present in this collection as photocopies or on microfilm. Not every document featured in the edition is currently represented here, as many were on microfilm on loan from the owning repositories for one-time reference use by the project, and such reels have been returned to the owning repositories.
Biographical / Historical
Best known as president of the Confederacy during the American Civil War, Jefferson Davis served in the Mexican War, in the House of Representatives and the Senate, and was secretary of war under Franklin Pierce. After the Civil War he became a symbol of the Lost Cause.
The Papers of Jefferson Davis, a documentary editing project based at Rice University in Houston, Texas, has prepared (1971-2015) a 14-volume edition of his letters and speeches, published by LSU Press.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the wealth of documentation identified from across the United States and beyond and assembled for the purpose of the publication of the Papers of Jefferson Davis, a 14-volume set, funded by the NHPRC, and other activities and persons, beginning in the 1960s and running through 2015. Many of the speeches and letters published in the edition, either in full or summarized, are present in this collection as photocopies or on microfilm. Not every document featured in the edition is currently represented here, as many were on microfilm on loan from the owning repositories for one-time reference use by the project, and such reels have been returned to the owning repositories.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Boxes 1-40 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
All file drawers and card catalog stored onsite.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by the Papers of Jefferson Davis Project after the last volume of the edition was published.
Arrangement
Copies of speeches and letters are arranged in boxes of microfilm grouped by owning repository and in file drawers arranged chronologically.
Researchers often begin their work by exploring the master card set which is arranged in chronological order, following the order of the documents featured in the 14-volume set. These cards contain information about the content of the document, as well as about the source of the original document, suggesting to the user whether the copy is in this collection as a photocopy, on microfilm, or in some cases is no longer part of this collection (cases when the owning repository took possession of the microfilm it has loaned for this project).
Other reference tools are arranged by date or alphabetically as appropriate, as can be seen by reviewing the box and file drawer listing in this finding aid.
The card catalog for the Papers of Jefferson Davis, supplementing the Vertical and Reference Files, is available in the reading room of the Woodson Research Center, and can be especially useful for topics such as locating Varina Davis documents and biographical sketches which were published in the multi-volume set.
Related Materials
Jefferson Davis Letters and related materials, MS 005, Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library, Rice University. (Finding aid online at http://archives.library.rice.edu/repositories/2/resources/5)
Jefferson Davis Project website includes valuale timeline and genealogical information: https://jeffersondavis.rice.edu/
Index Terms
Subjects
American Civil War (United States: 1861-1865); Politics and government
Document Types
photographs; letters (correspondence); notes; drawings (visual works); genealogies (histories); speeches
Places
Southern States
Subjects (Persons)
Davis, Jefferson; Davis, Varina Howell
- Series I: Documents, 1816-1907
  Scope and Contents
  All of the Jefferson Davis documents at the Woodson Research Center are copies except those in the Jefferson Davis Letters and related materials (MS 005, Woodson Research Center).
  The document files include everything the Jefferson Davis Project received in photocopy form, but only a relatively small percentage of prints from documents on microfilm.
  The document files are in chronological order by year.month.day, each in a manila envelope. Conjecturally dated items are filed at the end of the month or year. Documents from the secretary of war period (1853 - 1857) that cannot be reliably dated are filed at the end of 1857. Also check in "n.d." at the end of document files.
  The 3x5 pale yellow control slips in the envelopes may or may not reflect the copy actually used in the edition, but are useful for summaries.
  In addition to items to and from Jefferson Davis, the document files include the correspondence of Varina Howell Davis, Joseph E. Davis, and other family members. There are also letters of others about the Davises and contemporary issues. Some small collections of non-Jefferson/Varina Davis letters are in the genealogy files and vertical files. Two examples in the vertical files: William Preston Johnston letters and Dorsey Papers, the latter since folded into the Davis Collection at the Museum of the Confederacy (Davis was executor and heir of the Dorsey estate)–see numbers 2905-3081 in the checklist. In the genealogy files: Lise Mitchell Papers and Josie Alexander Collection.
  The copies come from hundreds of repositories and private owners. Many Davis collections - for example, those held by the Museum of the Confederacy (now located at the Va. Hist. Soc.), Tulane, Library of Congress, Duke, Transylvania, and the U. of Alabama - number in the hundreds or thousands.
  There are typed item by item inventories in the three ring binders for dozens of repositories. They are often helpful in identifying specific letters (where they may be filed, for example) and in determining ownership.
  We cannot allow the copying of any manuscripts except those owned by the Rice University, Davis family members, Library of Congress, and the National Archives. Only if the researcher secured permission from the owner, whether repository or individual, can a copy be made from our copy. Copying of typescripts, transcriptions, and printed versions is permitted.
  Many privately owned documents have entered or re-entered the marketplace since we secured our copies (see 89.2.2, to Martin W. Philips). Likewise, entire collections have been deaccessioned and sold, among them the Forbes Magazine Collection and the Dallas Historical Society collection of Davis / John H. Reagan letters.
  Many other names of collections and repositories have changed. Examples: "Confederate Museum" became Museum of the Confederacy and is now part of the American Civil War Museum; "Chicago Historical Society" is now the Chicago History Museum. The Gilder / Lehrman Collection moved from the Pierpont Morgan Library to the New York Historical Society.
  All copies received from the Filson Club (Filson Historical Society, Louisville) were returned to the Filson as a condition of use. Some were transcribed and the typescripts are in the document files.
  Ownership of the originals sometimes changes, in which case the envelope usually has multiple copies of the same item. See 80.11.22, to Capen, for an example of copies received from two different owners.
  Most prints of documents from microfilm made with old wet process microfilm reader/printers were discarded.
  Not all transcriptions in envelopes were prepared by Davis Project staff. In general, those on yellow or blue paper were. Except for the letters printed in full in the edition, most have not been proofread. Sometimes there is more than one document in an envelope–enclosure, letter or transmittal, letters on the same subject, for examples. The other letters are identified on the envelope and identified as "f/w" (filed with) in the database. See 61.6.13 from Harris. It happens occasionally that we don't have either the transmittal letter or that one is a photocopy and the other is on film or vice versa.
  Variant versions of the same item are filed together - sender's copy, recipient's copy, printed version, etc.
  Two documents from the same writer on the same day are filed together. Occasionally, a "permission to print" document is filed with the letter: 74.12.2, Varina to J. W. Garrett is an example. Otherwise, permission authorizations are in the correspondence files.
  "cat." on a document envelope means only an autograph dealer's catalog description is within.
  Sometimes there is a manuscript copy on microfilm. "cat. only" means we do not have a manuscript copy.
  "print" and "print only"–same as "cat." and "cat. only"
  "lost letters" on envelope: one of the letters stolen from Davis' library in Mississippi in 1863 [most of them, eventually turned over to William T. Sherman, form the core of the Davis Collection in the Library of Congress]
  "Rowland" on envelope: printed in the 1923 edition of Davis' papers
  "Private Ls" or "Priv Letters" or a variation of same means Hudson Strode's edition. His transcriptions are not accurate, so use with care. "DP 6:253.54" on envelope: printed in our edition, Davis Papers, volume 6, pages 253 to 254
  "Addenda, Vol. 9" on envelope: arrived after publication of volume in which it belongs chronologically and in time to be included in Addenda section of Volume 9, but not necessarily selected for inclusion in that Addenda section.
  All documents are recorded in spreadsheets, accessible to Woodson staff for reference purposes.
  - Subseries A: Documents on microfilm
    General
    The letter and letter-number codes in square brackets here represent the Davis Project's accession codes used for microfilm as they came in from the owning repository. The master document card set and the document envelopes make reference to these microfilm reel codes and go on to include frame numbers.
    - Virginia State Library [AP] (Box 1)
    - North Carolina Archives [AQ] (Box 1)
    - National Archives [AS] (Box 1)
    - Harvard University [AT] (Box 1)
    - National Archives [BX, BY, BZ, CA, CB] (Box 1)
    - Mississippi Archives [CC] (Box 1)
    - Historical Society of Pennsylvania [CD] (Box 1)
    - National Archives [CE, CF, CG, CH, CI, CJ, CK, CL, CM, CN, CO] (Box 1)
    - Georgia Archives [CP, CQ] (Box 1)
    - National Archives [GL, GM, GN, GO, GP, GQ, GR, GS, GU, GV, GW] (Box 1)
    - LSU [GX] (Box 1)
    - National Archives [JH, JI, JJ, JK, JL, JM, JN, JO, JP, JQ, JR] (Box 1)
    - Virginia Historical Society [JS] (Box 1)
    - Confederate Museum [JT, JU, JV, JW, JX, JY, JZ] (Box 1)
    - National Archives [KA, KB, KC, KD, KE, KF, KG, KH, KI, KJ] (Box 2)
    - Mississippi Archives [KK, KL] (Box 2)
    - Iowa Archives [KM] (Box 2)
    - Mississippi Archives [KN] (Box 2)
    - University of California, Berkeley [KO] (Box 2)
    - Huntington Library [KP] (Box 2)
    - Alabama Archives [KQ, KR] (Box 2)
    - Transylvania University [KS] (Box 2)
    - New York Historical Society [KT] (Box 2)
    - Mississippi Archives [KU] (Box 2)
    - National Archives [KV, KW, KX, KY, KZ, LA. LB, LC] (Box 2)
    - New York Historical Society [LD] (Box 2)
    - National Archives [LE, LF, LG, LH, LI, LJ, LK] (Box 2)
    - New York Public Library [MB] (Box 2)
    - National Archives [MC, MD, ME, MF, MG, MI, MJ, MK] (Box 2)
    - US Military Academy [ML, MM] (Box 2)
    - National Archives [PJ, PK, PL, PM, PN] (Box 2)
    - Library of Congress [PO, PP] (Box 2)
    - National Archives [PQ, PR] (Box 2)
    - National Archives [PS, PT, PU, PV, PW, PX, PY, PZ, QA, QB, QC] (Box 3)
    - Iowa Archives [QD] (Box 3)
    - Library of Congress, R.E. Lee Papers [QE] (Box 3)
    - National Archives [XH, XI, XJ, XK] (Box 3)
    - Duke University [XL, XM] (Box 3)
    - LSU [XN, XO] (Box 3)
    - Jennings, Nine Years of Democratic Rule in Mississippi (Box 3)
    - Library of Congress, Barbee Papers [XQ, XR] (Box 3)
    - Walthall, Sketch of the Life and Character of the President of the Confederate States (Box 3)
    - Confederate Museum [XT] (Box 3)
    - Vermilya, The Battles of Mexico [XX] (Box 3)
    - Moody, History of the Mexican War (Box 3)
    - Personal tax rools, Warren County, MS, 1818-36 [YB, YC] (Box 3)
    - Congressional Directory, 31st-36th Congress (Box 3)
    - Moore, Dictionary of Quotations [YE] (Box 3)
    - Mississippi Archives [YF] (Box 3)
    - Mississippi Archives (1845 Warren County census) [YG] (Box 3)
    - Library of Congress [YH] (Box 3)
    - Mississippi Archives, State of MS vs. H.A. Johnson, 1853 [YI] (Box 3)
    - Memphis State University (Univ. of Memphis) [ZA, ZB] (Box 3)
    - Tulane University [ZC-ZN] (Box 3)
    - Tulane University [ZO-AAB] (Box 4)
    - [Alexander] Jefferson Davis Since His Capture [AAC] (Box 4)
    - University of North Carolina, T. Bragg Papers [AAD] (Box 4)
    - Rawson, "Party Politics in MS, 1850-60" [B-30] (Box 4)
    - Hinton, "Military Career of General John E. Wool" [B-31] (Box 4)
    - Young, "Mississippi Whigs, 1834-60" [B-32] (Box 4)
    - Massachusetts Historical Society, Henshaw Narrative[B-33] (Box 4)
    - Muldowny, "Administration of Jefferson Davis as Secretary of War" [B-34] (Box 4)
    - National Archives [C-1, C-2, C-3, C-4, C-5, C-6, C-7, C-8, C-9, C-10, C-11, C-12, E-1, E-2, E-12, E-13, E-14] (Box 4)
    - 1850 census, Adams County, MS [E-15] (Box 4)
    - 1850 census, Hinds County, MS [E-16] (Box 4)
    - 1850 census, Marshall County, MS [E-17] (Box 4)
    - 1850 census, Warren and Wilkinson counties, MS [E-18] (Box 4)
    - National Archives [E-19, E-20] (Box 4)
    - 1845 MS census [E-21] (Box 4)
    - 1850 census DC, wards 1-4 [E-22] (Box 4)
    - 1850 census DC, wards 5-7 and rest of DC [E-23] (Box 4)
    - University of Kentucky, Henry Clay Jr. diary [E-24] (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan, Davis speeches, 1848-50 [E-25] (Box 4)
    - Virginia State Library (Library of Virginia), Lee-Davis correspondence [E-26] (Box 4)
    - National Archives [E-27] (Box 4)
    - University of Memphis [E-28] (Box 4)
    - CSA Senate and House Journals [E-29] (Box 4)
    - Tennessee Archives, Dahlgren Papers [E-30] (Box 4)
    - Memphis State University: Jefferson Davis-Joel Addison Hayes, Jr. family papers, 1864-1882 (Box 5)
    - Jefferson Davis papers in the National Archives, duplicate copies
      This set duplicates the National Archives reels accounted for in boxes 1-4, and are being kept as back up.
      - Before March 8, 1853 (Box 5)
      - 1824-1851 (rolls 1- 48; missing 47) (Box 5)
      - 1824-1851 (rolls 49-92; missing 62, 81) (Box 6)
  - Subseries B: Photocopied documents, 1816-1907
    Documents filed in date order, as noted on the envelope containing each document.
    - 1816-June 1832 (Drawer 1)
    - 1833-1845 (Drawer 2)
    - 1846 (Drawer 3)
    - 1847- June 1848 (Drawer 4)
    - 1848 June - 1849 (Drawer 5)
    - 1850 (Drawer 6)
    - 1851-1852 (Drawer 7)
    - 1853, January - July (Drawer 8)
    - 1853 August - 1854 January (Drawer 9)
    - 1854 February - December (Drawer 10)
    - 1855 (Drawer 11)
    - 1856 January - October (Drawer 12)
    - 1856 November - 1858 (Drawer 13)
    - 1859-1860 (Drawer 14)
    - 1861 January - June (Drawer 15)
    - 1861 July - December (Drawer 16)
    - 1862 January - April (Drawer 17)
    - 1862 May - August (Drawer 18)
    - 1862 September - December (Drawer 19)
    - 1863 January - May (Drawer 20)
    - 1863 June - September (Drawer 21)
    - 1863 October - December (Drawer 22)
    - 1864 January - April (Drawer 23)
    - 1864 May - August (Drawer 24)
    - 1864 September - December (Drawer 25)
    - 1865 January - May (Drawer 26)
    - 1865 - 1866 June (Drawer 27)
    - 1867-1868 (Drawer 28)
    - 1869-1870 (Drawer 29)
    - 1871-1873 (Drawer 30)
    - 1874-1876 (Drawer 31)
    - 1877-1878 September (Drawer 32)
    - 1878 October - 1879 (Drawer 33)
    - 1880-1881 (Drawer 34)
    - 1882-1883 (Drawer 35)
    - 1884-1885 (Drawer 36)
    - 1886-1887 June (Drawer 37)
    - 1887 July - 1888 (Drawer 38)
    - 1889-1894 (Drawer 39)
    - 1895-1907, and undated (Drawer 40)
- Series II: Reference tools for accessing documents, 1815-2015
  - Subseries A: Master card set for documents in Papers of Jefferson Davis (5"x8")
    The boxed 5x8 slips (Jefferson Davis items) and the 3x5 slips in the card catalog (Varina Davis) are arranged chronologically and are the resources most read and copied by researchers, who use them as a guide to the document files and microfilm.
    - 1846-1850 (Box 7)
    - 1851-1853 April (Box 8)
    - 1853 May - August (Box 9)
    - 1853 September - December (Box 10)
    - 1854 January - March (Box 11)
    - 1854 April - July (Box 12)
    - 1854 August - December (Box 13)
    - 1855 January - March 11 (Box 14)
    - 1855 March 12 - July (Box 15)
    - 1855 August - December (Box 16)
    - 1856 January - March (Box 17)
    - 1856 April - July 15 (Box 18)
    - 1856 July 16 - December (Box 19)
    - 1857 (Box 20)
    - 1858-1859 (Box 21)
    - 1860 (Box 22)
    - 1861 January - June (Box 23)
    - 1861 July - December (Box 24)
    - 1862 January - June (Box 25)
    - 1862 July - December (Box 26)
    - 1863 January - June (Box 27)
    - 1863 July - December (Box 28)
    - 1864 January - June (Box 29)
    - 1864 July - December (Box 30)
    - 1865-1869 (Box 31)
    - 1870 - 1876 (Box 32)
    - 1877-1880 (Box 33)
    - 1881-1885 (Box 34)
    - 1886-1889 (Box 35)
    - Varina Davis documents master card set (3x5" cards) (Drawer JD card catalog in reading room)
  - Subseries B: Newspaper clippings (copies) files
    Newspaper articles,some printed on thermal paper, are filed in chronological order. Many of the 3"x5" notes in the Papers of Jefferson Davis card catalog unit and 5"x8" cards refer to these prints.
    Newspaper sources for items published in The Papers of Jefferson Davis, usually speeches and interviews, are in the document files. Some, especially those relating to Davis family genealogy or to specific events in Davis' life, are now in the genealogy and vertical files.
    Many newspapers represented in these files are now available in digital format, but most-- particularly those from smaller markets--are not.
    Fondren Library has cataloged the Davis Project's collection of newspapers on microfilm, notably pre-1861 Mississippi papers and Richmond papers of 1861-65, likewise the collection of pre-1861 city directories on fiche.
    - 1815-1849 (Drawer 41)
    - 1850-1862 (Drawer 42)
    - 1863-1866 (Drawer 43)
    - 1867-1881 (Drawer 44)
    - 1882-2015 (bulk 1882-1899) (Drawer 45)
    - (drawers awaiting future newspaper additions) (Drawer 46-48)
  - Subseries C: Reference / subject files
    Jefferson Davis Reference files are often referenced in the 3x5" slips in the card catalog.
    - Biography, bibliography, property (Drawer 49)
    - Childhood, education, military, political career, Mexican War (Drawer 50)
    - Senate, U.S. Civil War, Secretary of War (Drawer 51)
    - Flight and capture, prison, trial, Canada, travel, Beauvoir, death (Drawer 52)
  - Subseries D: Vertical files
    Related Materials
    See also the A-Z drawers in the Papers of Jefferson Davis card catalog, Woodson Research Center reading room.
    Vertical files: persons, places, events, including some printed sources such as pamphlets and Confederate imprints, and typescripts.
    Individual females are filed and identified under their last married names–especially important for relatives such as Florida Ann Davis McCaleb Laughlin (niece) and Lucinda Farrar Davis Davis Stamps (sister), and close connections such as Inez Routh Ellis Gordon Thompson Peckham. In a couple of cases, there are vertical files on women under their husbands' names (Inez, for instance). In the vertical files, husbands' names are sometimes first, mainly because that's usually how to find people on censuses. Always wise to check the 3x5 slips (document and reference) for all surnames.
    - Files: Aberdeen - Boyle (Drawer 53)
    - Files: Bragg - Churchill (Drawer 54)
    - Files: Civil War - Davis Museums Association (Drawer 55)
    - Files: Deacon - Fixary (Drawer 56)
    - Files: Fleming - Gwin (Drawer 57)
    - Files: Hampton - Ives (Drawer 58)
    - Files: Jackson - Limber (Drawer 59)
    - Files: Lincoln - McRae (Drawer 60)
    - Files: Meade - Niles (Drawer 61)
    - Files: Noland - Pyles (Drawer 62)
    - Files: Quackenboss - Sprague (Drawer 63)
    - Files: Stafford - Volck (Drawer 64)
    - Files: Waddill - Zincke (Drawer 65)
  - Subseries E: Family and Genealogy files
    [Individual folders to be listed soon.]
    Many family members in the genealogical charts (Vols. 1 and 4 appendixes and online) do not have biographical sketches in the edition.
    Divided into separate folders for Jefferson's parents and siblings in birth order (Matilda #8 died young). The folders are a hodge-podge of information, compiled over fifty years and derived from printed sources and primary documents; there are also primary documents in the files, such as gravestone photographs. Vertical files and the 3x5 slips (information and document control slips) also should be consulted about individuals.
    Some family members--Joseph E. Davis, for example--have vertical files in addition to information in the genealogy folders. Joseph E. Davis' probate file is filed with genealogy since it involves so many relatives.
    There are many repeated and similar names in the family: Mary Ellen, Ellen Mary, Lucinda Jane, Jane Lucinda, Hugh Robert, Robert Hugh, for example, as well as several namesakes of Joseph Emory and Jefferson Davis.
    There are allied materials such as folders for the Howell family, on Davis' first and second marriages, Varina Howell Davis, Varina Anne Davis, [great-niece] Lise Mitchell's journal (Tulane), published and unpublished Davis family histories, and other collections of family papers, including contemporary letters.
    - First marriage ceremony and Beechland (Drawer 66)
    - First marriage ceremony Taylor family reminiscences, including Trist Wood papers (Drawer 66)
    - First marriage ceremony, articles and correspondence, 1881-1966 (Drawer 66)
    - Second marriage (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: primary sources, belongings, images (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: memoir, 1890 (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: manuscripts, typescripts, and fragments (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: book, Etiquette for all Occasions (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: book, Grasshopper War (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: newspaper articles and other writings (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: secondary sources and bibliography, 1906-1979, 1992 (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Howell Davis: secondary sources and bibliography, 1980s- (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Anne Davis: primary sources and images (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Anne Davis: secondary sources (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Anne Davis: writings (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Anne Davis: Cita Cook articles (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Anne Davis: article, Heath Hardage - Symbol of Sacrifice (Drawer 66)
    - Varina Anne Davis: article by Tommie LaCavera, "Varina Anne Winnie Davis" (Drawer 66)